[Music]
blessings everyone this is chris kendall
from therawadvanish.com registered
holistic nutritionist raw food lifestyle
coach and raw chef today i'm going to
make you a falafel burger feast let's
get into it maybe i'll like it raw
raw advantage likes it wrong
oh baby i like it raw
yeah baby i like it wrong
all right well i hope you're ready for
this amazing falafel burger feast it's
one of my all-time favorites always a
hit whether it's in the burger patties
or in the falafel ball kind of pattern
whatever you want to do you can use it
both ways but i'm going to share my
quickest easiest way to make this recipe
i can literally just throw it together
and throw the dehydrator and it'll be
ready for dinner you will want to start
this at least the day before because
we're sprouting a little bit of
chickpeas and if you want you can spread
them for two or three days but other
than that you just start the morning of
the day you're gonna have the feast and
just so you know this recipe serves two
to four people makes ten perfect falafel
burger patties and a nice side salad to
share let's get right into it the main
part of this recipe is the actual
falafel burger patties i'm going to give
you a couple bonus sauce recipes at the
end like raw vegan hummus
a mango chutney and a little bit of a
hot sauce with all the fixings and
toppings and you know kind of bun
lettuce bun to make this feast complete
but where this all starts is the falafel
burger patties and to do that we're
going to use two groupings of
ingredients the first one you're going
to want to focus on is the wet
ingredients zucchini 0.5 pounds or 230
gram soaked chickpeas just shy of one
cup pumpkin seeds one half of a cup red
onion point one three pounds or sixty
grams one lemon or a quarter cup juice
one teaspoon of cumin and one clove of
garlic and we're gonna start by just
blending all these up until they're nice
creamy and smooth it's always helpful to
start with the wettest ingredients first
and the things that are going to blend
the fastest so we'll put the zucchini in
the very bottom
so special note a few days before we
started with one half of a cup of dried
chickpeas soaked them overnight and then
just rinsed them two to three times a
day for two days to sprout and what we
ended up with is this much now for the
falafel burger patties we're gonna use
just shy of one cup of soaked and or
sprouted chickpeas and then we're gonna
save a heaping third of a cup for the
raw hummus on the side for later we'll
put the soaked sprouted chickpeas in
next it's just shy of one cup a little
bit less than a half a cup of pumpkin
seeds about a third a pound or 60 grams
of red onion
optional one full lemon's worth of juice
or about a quarter cup four tablespoons
optional one garlic and a heaping
teaspoon of cumin now if you don't want
cumin you could use curry powder instead
or neither i love to use my bio chef
vacuum container on my vitamix i have a
whole bunch of information and videos
below on that so we're just going to
vacuum this up
and we blend it all up
all right and now comes the really fun
part and part where you can save a lot
of time we got all these chunky
ingredients that create the texture and
extra flavor that we know and love with
falafel so cauliflower 0.6 pound or 272
grams
zucchini 0.5 pound 230 grams 1 carrot
0.25 pound or 112 grams walnuts 0.22
pounds or 100 grams red onions 0.11
pounds or 50 grams parsley 0.05 pounds
or 20 grams cilantro 0.1 pound or 45
grams an oregano 1 tablespoon dry so
we're just going to take all these
ingredients starting with the hardest at
the bottom going up to the softest and
just pulse them in using the tamper of
the vitamix now
the other option which takes a heck of a
lot more time is to either hand grate
finely chop or one at a time chuck these
into a food processor like this guy back
here
and create a pill like texture and then
just mix both the batter and the chunks
together but it saves you a heck of a
lot of time just to throw it all into
the vitamix now one important bit of
information if you're using the biochef
vacuum container on your vitamix the
tamper goes a little too low so you only
want to put the lid on just a little bit
otherwise you may risk hitting the
blades with the tamper
otherwise it's just easier
to use the regular vitamix container so
i made this recipe just so that
everything will fit in one vitamix and
create the perfect amount for a party so
let's start with the cauliflower
and the carrots
zucchini
red onion
walnuts which are optional if you want
to keep it lower fat you don't need to
put them in there you can just
substitute that for some extra
cauliflower
and we'll save the herbs for last now
the secret to this is just to keep the
vitamix speed dial between about a two
to a four i like to have it set at the
three
turn it on and just use the tamper just
push everything in there
you want to take a little bit of time
get every single corner to make sure
that all of it is just pulsed up into
little bits
you don't want to go too fast we're not
looking for a puree
this not only saves a lot of time in the
making but also in the cleanup
[Music]
now that we've got it pretty decently
cut up
we'll add in the herbs one tablespoon
dried oregano
small bunch of parsley and about a bunch
of cilantro
same thing
with the herbs i like to give a quick
few little blast just to break up any
little bits
push them in
and you want to use the tamper to mix
the batch up a bit
seriously amazing and there you have it
we're ready to start making patties so
what you're going to need
is two excalibur trays with some teflex
sheets on top
i just actually got these teflex sheets
off of amazon nine of them for 15 or 20
bucks really darn good deal
any non-stick kind of thing even
parchment paper can work but you're
going to want to start with that you'll
see why
all we do is take a half of a cup it's a
perfect size for a burger
fill up
it's okay if it's just a little bit more
and we put that
on one corner of the sheet
and use the spoon
to slightly flatten it
to a burger patty just repeat
just look at those beauties you can
generally fit you know about five per
sheet but i like to put three really
close the front because those will be
dried first and you'll see the next
steps as we go and look at that 10
perfect falafel burger patties all we
got to do is pop them in an excalibur to
hydrate or like this
i like to start the first half hour of
the drying at 1 30 and then drop to 118
for the rest of the drying time all
right so it's been two hours and it's
time to flip these over they're just dry
enough on the top that when i put them
on another sheet without the teflex then
it's not going to totally stick and fall
apart but i have a little trick for you
the three at the front are a little more
dry and the two in the back aren't quite
as dry so what i'm going to do is use my
hands carefully to push each of these
two back burgers over and one down and
then i'm going to flip it onto another
tray so that these in the back are in
the front
and there we go we'll just do this to
the other one and put them back in the
dehydrator
well it's just the waiting game now and
while we wait why not make those three
bonus sauces plus i want to get it done
before it's dark out so we can get dark
so early right now it's crazy so i like
to make them in a certain order you can
make them in any order but i find this
makes it easier for cleaning as i just
don't clean the blender between so the
first one we're gonna make is some mango
chutney so for this recipe you're going
to need mango 0.83 pounds or 375 grams
persimmon 0.19 pound or 85 grams 1 4 of
lemon 1 tablespoon juice
ginger 1 tablespoon red onion two
tablespoons
if you can't find ripe mango you can use
frozen mango you just want to thaw it
first and otherwise if it's a different
season you can use really nice sweet
juicy nectarine or even peach right now
this mango is just okay so i'm actually
adding the persimmon if you don't have
persimmons you could add a date or two
and if the mango is incredibly sweet you
don't need either so just play with it
depending upon the ingredients you have
with what i have here i'm going to add
in about
a third of the mango
the whole persimmon
the lemon juice
and about half of the onion and ginger
we're going to blend that up nice and
smooth
and then we'll add the remaining mango
and red onion and ginger
just a special note if you don't want to
add any onion you can you can omit it
you can otherwise use green onion i find
the red onion to be one of the mildest
nicest tasting onions out there
otherwise there's the maui sweet as well
and then we're just gonna pulse this
into a kind of a thick chunky
consistency
smells delicious that's it for the
chutney
i could use a spatula but i'm too lazy
and anyways i don't mind having just a
little bit of the residue in time for
the hot sauce so for the hot sauce
you'll need tomatoes .77 pound 350 grams
red onion two tablespoons one date or
.06 pounds or 23 grams one quarter lemon
one tablespoon of juice sun-dried tomato
point zero two five pounds or ten grams
and hot pepper to taste
you can use any tomatoes you want i just
love these cherries or grape tomatoes as
they're really really dang sweet and
tasty we'll just dump them right in
add some date equivalent to one the
jewel
the red onion
sun-dried tomato
as much hot pepper as you want this is a
spicy jalapeno so half as good
and the lemon
blend to completely smooth
perfecto
you can smell the spiciness oh my
perfect now
if you like your spicer you can add a
bit more if you want a little bit more
tangy you can add a bit more lemon if
you want a teeny bit more sweet add a
little bit more date if you want it a
little bit more savory or a little
thicker add a teeny bit more sun-dried
tomato
you can you can flavor however you want
i'm just gonna fill it up in this bottle
there we go i'm also give it a test day
tell them canadian eh
now it's time for the hummus all right i
know you're all waiting for that hummus
it's definitely a crowd favorite and one
that i haven't shared any video of yet
so what you're gonna need for this
recipe is zucchini .5 pounds or 230
grams soaked chickpeas heaping one third
of a cup one half of a lemon or two
tablespoons of juice sesame seeds two
tablespoons smoked paprika one teaspoon
and a clove of garlic
so as you can see i'm a little bit lazy
i haven't washed the blender because i
don't mind just a little tinge of the
hot sauce in the hummus but if you're
serving to people who do not like any
spicy even the slightest bit then you
probably want to wash that out first
just like the others i'm going to put
the most watery easy to blend
ingredients in first so zucchini and
lemon here we go and those beautiful
spreaded chickpeas
sesame seeds if you're going for extra
low fat you can cut this in half or you
can use about half the quantity of
quality tahini
option a large clove of garlic
hummus is meant to be garlicky and the
optional smoked paprika
blend till smooth and creamy
look at that thick and creamy hummus
perfect
this is when you could use a spatula
and there we have it three perfect
sauces for the falafel burger feast
just a little shuffle magoo
all right we're here post bath and the
burgers are almost done so what we have
here is two tomatoes half of a cucumber
some sprouts and a big old head of
romaine lettuce let's get those fixings
all ready we're just going to take the
10 outer leaves off of here i'm going to
nibble the bottoms off
now
each one of these
it's a bang
the heart of the romaine we're going to
chop up finely
knead the bum if you want dirty
just a nice little side salad that of
course you can add some extra greens too
some chopped tomatoes whatever you like
but this is just
to use up that extra i could just put in
the fridge but i'm gonna eat it
take cucumber just slice them into
circles and let's make some tomato
slices and here we go we're all ready
for the burgers well the moment truth is
here it's been seven hours since the
start you could dry more but these
burgers are done perfect to me
so i'm just gonna dress these up
come come get a little closer let's do
this together creasing that leaf just
right so that it folds easy putting all
the burgers on there some hummus then a
bit of tomato and the chutney the
cucumbers the sprouts and hot sauce
look at that beauty just look at that
beauty i i think i think you got the
picture i'm just gonna hit repeat
but i can't handle it i'm gonna
i'm just gonna eat one more right now
i'm just gonna smash it back let's see
what do you think what do you think
[Music]
i think you guys are going to love this
i hope you enjoy the video i hope you
enjoy making these and sharing them with
others and just so you know i mean this
recipe is for 10 burger patties
you don't have to eat them all you can
freeze as many of them as you want in
fact you can double this and freeze a
whole bunch and then you just pop in the
dehydrator for about 30 minutes to 45
minutes to thaw out and get ready again
for a really quick falafel burger feast
so
well
and i almost forgot
invariably you'll have a little bit left
over of the hummus and the chutney and
what i do with it is actually use it in
the salad and
sometimes there's enough that you can
spruce up the salad and add more volume
to it so that everyone has a little side
salad because again this can easily feed
two to four maybe even five people five
people two burgers each inside salad
just depends how hungry people are
burger falafel party
but again i really hope you love this
recipe if you do give it a thumbs up you
know hit that subscribe and that little
bell button give me a comment below let
me know what you want to see more of and
as always wishing you much peace love
and seasonal fruit
falafel burger feast
i hope you really enjoy it
don't forget to check out my raw recipes
playlist in the top left the video just
for you in the top right subscribe for
more videos in the bottom right and get
your three free ebooks in the bottom
left
grab your free raw recipe app available
on iphone and android with over 100 free
raw recipes common fruit and vegetable
calorie breakdown freaking raw some food
combining shopping cart function and so
much more